[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
boom all right everyone welcome
to the stoa uh the store is the place
for us to cohere and dialogue about what
matters most at the nice edge at this
very moment and i'm peter limberg the
steward
of the stoa and this is a first part of
a new
sensemaker and residence series for the
month of october
we have quite a few sense makers in
residence for
october including benito roy and daniel
schmachtenberger
and today we have a meta modern
superstar daniel gertz
um and he's doing something called meta
modern deep dives which is going to give
us
a different take on the meta-modern
scene which includes art spirituality
sexuality and faith
um so today laura uh
whitzigg uh better known as llw
who has been uh stow a super user here
and a big fan of metamodernism will be
emceeing today
so i will hand it to laura and she will
uh introduce
daniel and introduce the q a protocol
and this will be
90 minutes but it might end a little bit
earlier just to give everyone
some sense of the time so that being
said i will take
lauren
thanks peter uh all right
so hi everyone i'm laura out in san
francisco california and i'll be your mc
today
um so welcome daniel
we are very excited to have you back
uh so daniel is part of the metamoderna
think tank publisher of the books the
listening society and nordic ideology as
penned by that infamous meta-modern man
of mystery
ponzi freynot the books are part of a
forthcoming series a six called a
meta-modern guide to politics that lays
out a possible way forward through the
complex web of problems we are facing
for the benefit of humanity and all
sentient
beings however this series won't be a
political metamodernism 101
instead dany will be taking us on some
little modern deep dives into art
spirituality
sexuality and faith this is your
invitation
to tread out onto thinner ice of this
emergent culture
so the way this session will work is
daniel will start us off with a
presentation which will be followed by a
q a
if you have a question for daniel during
or after the presentation just drop it
in the chat box
please start it with a question or a
queue so we can easily find it
also please note this session will be
recorded and posted on youtube so if you
would like the question to be asked on
your behalf
just indicate that in the chat
without further ado uh welcome
daniel
i am unmuting myself uh hey everyone
thanks uh for being here um
so where to start so
this is a series on uh mad and modern
deep
dives meaning that um and thank you very
much for for intro with
both and and for the opportunity uh
both of you um so
um we'll try and do stuff we don't
do in the books um so there that we we
have
hansi frank and he he kind of has this
we in in hansi's philosophy
there's kind of an engine and then like
uh
we could try and pick that engine apart
and see where
what it really is and where it's at and
how it functions and develop it at depth
um but given that the world is where it
is
um me and other
metamodernists have primarily focused on
like okay we we kind of get roughly the
new philosophy
there are a lot of details and depths to
be to be developed
we need to hurry history along a little
bit and we need to
um run a little bit put put the card
before the horse
sometimes uh so and start inventing
stuff for politics for for the world and
so on
which is dangerous we're not there
culturally we're not there
psychologically etc etc
uh and yet there's an urgency because of
the climate change thing and because of
a bunch of other existential risks
because of institutional decay
that has to do with with the internet
and with the global society
so this particular day
or well so so so uh peter asked
about uh what what could you be talking
about on this uh
on this since maker residence thing and
um
i thought about it it's like well i
always end up saying roughly what's in
the books right
and there we do have lots of other
things
uh metamodernism can be applied to other
and um and there is a sensibility
from which all of this stuff comes and
particularly what's usually most
interesting to be talking about
just not hasn't been the highest
priority for uh for writing and stuff
is stuff like this subtle stuff this the
touchy stuff
like hmm what are the layers of
of phenomenological experience
uh well wilbur calls them four bodies
how does that translate into a secular
realized philosophy into a a new
spirituality and
how how is spirituality to be reinvented
how is religion to be invented and i
thought well the best way to start
is actually some of these themes will be
touched upon in the next book
the best way to start is in the
already profound and deep and important
part
but not that deep so we'll go into
the arts and aesthetics today um and
it's a critique that's leveled against
me sometimes wait wait a minute this guy
is in an art scholar and
and he hasn't even read all the other
meta modernists uh who who
who comment on all the netflix shows and
and literature and stuff and that's true
um what i bring to the table is
is not the details of each painting it's
basically only the world
viewed from a meta modern philosophical
standpoint and i also define that
differently than do of course
the dutch metamodernist scholars and so
on
um so what we'll be doing here
is we'll try to understand a few a few
core concepts
really of how the arts develop
and what is beauty
um and uh we'll we'll
be able to get a sense of
uh the meta memes what they are
as uh so modern society post modern
critique of
that and meta modernist we'll we'll try
to get a sense of that
as viscerally as possible so i would
like to share my screen if that's
all right uh yes i do have that
well sorry planning here you go um
aesthetics
so the title of this this little talk is
participatory beauty is the generator
function so another of the sense makers
daniel
schmuckenberger has this term the
generator function
and he says we have to change the
generator function of society
and generator function would be well
some kind of some kind of code or some
kind of uh
piece of well it's like a mathematical
equation that's at the center
or chord but maybe beyond our grasp
but which nevertheless generates all the
this like the structure of what's going
on what what we do
um and the easiest way
i would argue to get that generator
function what it is
is to get it intuitively um
ah yeah yeah thank you thank you we're
looking at
uh at the presentation mode uh so
one moment a slideshow from the
beginning
there you go um and
um
the the best way to try to get it is uh
thanks thanks somebody wrote to me
privately here
so the this generator function is
something like
hmm there is a fundamental logic
that steers roughly what goes on in a
kind of culture
and i call those different
those are different logics the meta
memes
so we go from from animistic
and the paleolithic times to to
faustian which well bronze age times
roughly and so on to um
and and iron age for that matter to
uh post-fastian which
is well in spiral and i'm just called
blue and in
traditional societies where we have this
these big religions and so on
from there on to modern and from modern
to post-modern from modern
post-modern to meta-modern and at each
stage
the generator function changes um
so um and and there it's a there's an
easy way to to to see that
or to understand that and it's that
look at the pyramids
um in early egypt empire
[Music]
and then fast forward 1000 years
look at the pyramids so the new pyramids
build 1000 years later
they have roughly the same hieroglyphs
they'll be a little bit more intricate
but that's it
you know it will look as though the same
person
had made it maybe just a few years later
from our perspective
it will look as though the same person
has made
the art that was made a thousand years
later
now egypt is a maybe an unfair example
as a
was a highly highly conservative society
but
you can do the same thing for uh for a
lot of the early
um early societies out there you can
look at african art
and you you there's just no no
way in hell you'll you'll
mix it up with viking art it just just
doesn't happen
they look so different and the viking
art looks fairly similar across
looks as though the same artist there
and then you can go to mesoamerica
then you can go to china then you can go
to the middle east
each of the civilizations have a
generator function
now um and they they
create art at a certain at a certain
degree of complexity or something if you
look at
today you can see this is a picasso
and then you can go and say this is a
pollock
etc the the particular artist will have
a thumbnail
which then differs because we're in a
much more complex society where in a
much more complex culture
we have a more complex generator
function so the degrees of freedom of
what can be created within culture
have increased um
so throughout we'll be playing this
little game um
and it's shouldn't be taken too
seriously it's kind of just the
background for the talk
um guess the meta meme well so we have
the
those uh those caves in france from
well they're very very old so uh and
they're
at the early animistic uh meta meme
most likely what what what makes them so
well we see that there are not yet
real monsters there the the
human mind is fairly close to
nature and undifferentiated from it and
has not yet differentiated out
a world of gods you can have animal
spirits
and these animals do seem to have
um well we're not sure maybe they're
moving around
maybe uh maybe they just tried to draw
many examples maybe they were practicing
maybe there's a spiritual element
to that they're transparent you can see
them uh
see many of them um but
uh they're they're highly alive and
there's not so many different elements
have been combined
looking at these two other ones if we
guess the meta meme
we would be at faustian or red or
um or in
a bronze age setting this is also like
google bronze hr
here so we see this
first figurine that we have been
starting to
we have started to combining many more
elements
and the second one also
we have is we are starting to combine
the fashion
of the person within this society
and uh we just
notice that it's not
close to what human beings look like
but at the same time it's
at some remove from natural society for
from from
the natural environment so
this is a pretty big jump though and
here
we get into the question what is beauty
well so what these people are doing are
is
not art in the in the
common sense of the term we wouldn't say
this is an artist because that's come
that comes much much later and it's only
a division
that happens in the 1800s with a with
modernity
or maybe maybe 1600s or or earlier
but um but in full
it hits home really only in the 1800s
when modernity hits home at
very very strongly and the artist
becomes a category onto him or herself
and art becomes a category in onto
itself
so here earlier it's not
differentiated from for instance
religion for us
art and religion are two different
things for these people not
so we also see that art is not trying to
do
not comment upon society etc uh we're
saying that we're seeing that it
expresses
this the society within it which it is
uh within within which it is placed
we go on guess the metamine
now this is very very different we've
made a very
long jump in
in time so
these are of course this is of course
also religious art
and it's not part of the modern period
it's part of the post-fasting
traditional
uh metamine nevertheless we can see
which civilization civilization it
belongs to it is
incredibly integral intricate
but there can be no doubt which
civilization
this is part of so you see again
that even though you've you've
increased a whole level of abstraction
and
here god is so abstract it's no longer a
figurine
we've gone far far it's no longer an
image of a person
it's just an abstract premonition of
what could be
what could be oh i can admit people now
so it's just an abstract premonition of
what the divine is it it points towards
the universal
it all goes to one point
and and this is of course islamic or or
arabic art and um
or maybe even person but it's an islamic
art
um and the the point here
is that there's such a huge
shift in abstraction from
uh the the god figurines there's a much
much much
more abstract um
thing going on generator function
so the sublime also reaches higher in a
way
it becomes more removed from everyday
life
and it reaches towards more
abstract or more otherworldly divinity
so beauty becomes more intricate
it coordinates more mastery
and it points towards a higher shared
pinnacle
so today's integral traditionalists for
instance and people on the far right
will hold that this was or in
christianity for instance with the
cathedral says this was the pinnacle of
civilization in a large cycle
because at this point um you had
the the the cathedrals being
um the top at the top of society
uh the the the the
creation of sublime beauty under some
kind of hierarchy
was uh the the
primary aim of society above all
else and there was nothing
there were no worldly powers to
challenge that
um so so they will argue that
since then it's been a downturn
now there are many we should be taking
that
that issue seriously and there are many
good counter arguments i
hope i can get back to that we can
discuss it a little bit
and there's a certain validity to that
concern
that we've lost this um
this unity
in the art projects this transcendence
of society
this uh this transcendence where
society itself and all of our governance
and all that we do
is for generations submitted
subdued by an aesthetic project
which is pretty awesome if you think
about it and and
i mean the the the far right there would
argue you walk through the louvre for
instance
or the intellectual far right anyway you
walk through the loop
and you compare it to
i don't know drab social democratic
uh brick buildings or or concrete
buildings in the
in in the communist east
and that's where equality got us that's
where democracy gets us because it's
rational it's for everyone
or or the blandness of the european
union
it has nothing of this sublimity of this
i mean if you go to the museum of the
european union it's absolutely boring
and and all the all the uh
all the monuments that that are that are
there i mean some of them are a little
bit cute but but
really very few people skip a heartbeat
over it right
um and of course it's because it tries
to be universal and
inclusive and not offensive
which is the opposite of art
ah i'm sorry i actually forgot the main
point
before i i am the main point
was when we look can i go back
now the more the for each such layer
what is beauty what is art art is
creation but is also than destruction
the more we add on each layer
the more we also destroy so the
higher transcendence will
require the greater destruction and this
is a this is a horrible horrible
nietzschean paradox but we can't escape
it so so this is
if we if we go to uh
let's see can i can i um uh
previous yeah if you go to this first
one
uh okay so you took some some cold
parts and you drew something but you
didn't really destroy the wall
you didn't you you messed up a little
some bits of coal right
to make a sculpture you had to dig out
this metal
you have to reshape it and not only did
you reshape
the metal and and extracted from from
much more much more from nature you
also messed up the categories is this a
human
being does it have animal eyes
we're not sure anymore the same goes for
the next one you know you have to ruin
the tree to to get there and here
once you get far enough in the i mean
this goes to many more layers but
once you get far enough you've smashed
the categories to bits
until you reach pure abstraction and
there's one universal god and it's
emptiness and it's silence and all you
can do
is follow this right um
so so this is what goes on with the
generator functions this generator
functions
they kick into place when things are
broken on the general on the
on the previous generator function
and they start generating culture out of
faster and and more
more complex
rate which means they create a wider
variety
which at the same time destroys much
more
and creates um creates higher complexity
um and then
when it comes to matter of preference
uh that's something else we'll get back
to that we'll get back to the to a
matter of preference
i'll find a better way to pause there
next one
and guess the meta meme uh well
so this is early modernity
and this is interesting because if you
look in
an arts book in a textbook of arts and
you or you
you go and have a college degree in arts
they'll tell you yeah so
modern modern is it's like picasso it's
early 20th century but
those were words that were invented in a
time
those words were those labels uh came to
be in a time before
we actually had a lot of um a lot of um
like developmental theories along these
lines
so they're quite an exact what they what
the reason they have those categories is
basically that
they feel that you're
at high modernity uh you have cars and
planes and people are walking around in
the malaya
malay of downtown
traffic and they're speaking on the
phone and they're
participating in democracies in the
capitalist market
and this art shows up at that time so of
course you're going to call it modern
art modernist art
now then the issue is that
um if you look at the meta memes
history is skewed or development is
skewed
um and
it takes 500 years at least for
modernity
to get from just a concept in the arts
to um a full
blown political system and there's a
logic to that
let's say there's a logic to modernity
it's
the logic is um well that's interesting
mr
premodernity tradition so you're saying
everything is pointing
can you guys see um my little pointer
i'm pointing to this little
top yeah so everything is pointing to
this one universal principle or the
truth and
there's one truth why wouldn't there be
well you're right well if it's so
universal
why can't we all look at it together
uh and and we can all recognize it for
when we just we don't have to get it
just from one source
then then it has to be truly universal
right and that's that's a
fundamental shift of modernity now that
happens in the arts before
it happens in first the scientific
revolution of the 1600s and then the
the enlightenment of the 1700s and then
through a bunch of social
and political revolutions of the 1800s
and then
yeah lances in the 1900s and a
full-blown
modern society the majority of the
population of which maybe only
mid-century
uh became predominantly secular in many
many countries right so
what are these images well they're
they're the
with the highest google ability this one
and they're in all the
they're in all the arts textbooks this
one is
dutch renaissance and this one is
italian renaissance
this one is dutch renaissance
is his name yes
and he's one of the major major names of
the dutch renaissance
and this is raphael now there are two
things
worth noticing here which are very very
i mean they say a lot about what
modernity truly
is and it's so fascinating that these
things show up
separately and in parallel
at the dawn of modernity well so
the most well-known is of course
uh is of course the
the italian renaissance now the italian
renaissance what it has
is perspective so you see this this is
of course
uh plato's academy by rafael
um or whatever it's called and
um and there is correct perspective in
it
so if you would look at a painting for
instance by
islamic artists a little bit earlier
you would have found that the the
the islamic artists drew the king bigger
even if he was
farther away why because well first of
all they didn't know perspective
but second of all because nature is not
differentiated
from culture and how here nature
revolts against culture talks back and
says
we have our own laws we have our own
space our own dimensions
if you have your social little life and
your little ideas
within within the larger framework of
nature you better place it
in these three dimensions so
and and that becomes kind of the the
playing field there
now that sounds a lot like something
uh one one moment if we look at the
other one
john van iack
well it's it's pretty fascinating
there's a little mirror there
where you can see the married couple or
newlyweds um
[Music]
from from the other side uh now what
the dutch renaissance did they always
they also approached this photographic
precision
i mean they're not quite photographed
yet but that's what they approached
and uh they did it by
just they broke up
whatever they were looking at into the
tiniest pixels and they looked at the
details and they added detail and they
added detail and added detail
until reality came back on the painting
including like minute details
like a mirror even the painter is then
there
so that the painter admits to being part
of this study and then of course we
could go into other
things that um yeah i'll
pause there i'm just saying that the
first one here
is a lot like deduction
meaning the scientific method of
deduction
wait a minute if this then that this
rule says that then
and the the figures in this
in this image to the right the raphael
image
are placed deductively
if this is placed there then according
to our own model
this should be placed there and at that
scale
you use a deductive model which is one
of the two
primary methods of science you go to the
left
you have used induction you have used
i'm gonna see i'm gonna add another case
is it right is it wrong
and basically you treat what you're
looking at as a bunch of pixels and
you're seeing
is this the same color as that yes it is
no it's not okay then i'll change it
and then you go like that until you have
depicted reality and voila
modern life comes out of the screen of
these two
images and into
first science and that's what i wanted
to say before
on on science then like and why was even
leonardo da vinci
so interested in science because he
wanted to be a better painter so we
could see and a sculpture
uh which was what led him to study
anatomy in the first place and then that
led him on a bunch of other concerns but
uh but the very fact that
uh i mean the the the
the doing or the uh the participation in
art
pulled forth uh the scientific endeavor
which i mean the scientific revolution
starts literally here
in north italy um
so so so there's a very close connection
there
and yeah and there you can really see
the art within the metame this is the
best and clearest example really
and it's kind of the kind of the
we know modernity so well because it's
so well studied
so and i think i mean hey it's not a
crusade i'm gonna fight
but maybe maybe someone somewhere out
there
would like to change our vocabulary we
shouldn't be calling
contemporary art modern art we should be
calling
picasso a modernist for instance
which brings us to of course guess the
metameme
um so i'll let you in on what i've
googled
um
well of course i googled picasso
i've googled um a google
pollock my googled world
and i go to google futurist painting i
actually didn't
didn't save the name but
futurist is the oldest one of these and
this one is the youngest one but looking
at the futurist painting
you see that well we've gone into
abstraction we've gone into abstract art
we've gone into contemporary art so
eventually the arts became photographic
uh
they started being post photographic so
they looked
in romantic time they started looking
more and more like
instagram like you had a filter on or
something and it looked like a little
bit more extra magical so you
notice and that kind of stuff still is
with us
to this day on i don't know fantasy
books and stuff
but uh eventually
that project breaks now you can actually
photograph and
and the artists become aware of
themselves
as such not as painters at the court
not as decorators of churches not as
uh expression expressers of religious
uh of religious truths uh
or or servants of the truth they become
artists
themselves and then there are a few then
core
themes so one here the first one is
modernity isn't still it's a moving
target and it's moving
faster and faster and we're going to be
able to shape that one we're going to be
able to change the narratives of that
one
so that's kind of the theme you can see
in futurist
uh in futurist paintings so and they
also futures tend to be one
want to be a little bit tough uh and uh
and they wanna uh show that
in this flurry and chaos will somehow
come out on top will somehow shape where
this whole thing is going
so of course there is a very close
connection between the earth this
early postmodern theme all of these are
of course
post-modern expressions of what i would
call post-modern art in terms of meta
memes so
even if it says something different in
the in the
art books in the textbooks on art i
would hold in terms of meta memes these
are
all within the post-modern meta meme and
again it's not because
society was post-modern just as
we didn't have modern society in in the
1400s
or fifteen hundreds in italy and and um
and uh the netherlands
uh so we didn't have post-modern society
in 1910 or whatever
um but but the point is that
the arts were already there they were
already criticizing the world were
already overturning
the modern order and the modern progress
and we're trying to shape it
and so on now if you go overboard with
trying to shaping modern society
and you combine it with some earlier not
meta memes but value means as we'll soon
get to
you uh you get in that art war against
reality and you want to
plaster the same aesthetics onto all of
reality
until the same simplified generator
function and that's
fascism so and this is
literally what they did hitler literally
designed
the the symbol of the of the nasdaq
party and and so on
and um i mean he didn't
invent the swastikas foster has been
around for thousands of years but he
literally designed it and drew that
thing with the coloring and so on and
then plus
got a lot of people to go along and
plastering this all over
anyway that's parathesis but it's worth
noting
now that if you look at picasso what
have we here
so he knows perspective but he re
consciously revolts against perspective
aha so you have perspective change
parallax view you have multiple
perspectives
you have a kind of surrealism that grows
from
you never know quite what's real um
you have that
art should should be revealing also of
the human being in her newness and
nakedness and that we are um
we are helpless uh um
in well we we are helpless when it comes
to maintaining our
our dick course and so on if the arts
really check us you know and and in the
same period you have of course
the post-modern artists are going to
revolt
against the modern category of art so
this duchamp guy goes and brings a
toilet
and puts it on the stage and or on a
pedestal and says
like look by definition this is art and
people are talking about it to this day
so the next year pollock so they
actually showed
in in research later on that uh
pollock's
paintings were you know just splash lots
of color that they're not random and
there's a progression
and he falls kind of fractal pattern and
this practical
fractals apparently get more and more
complex as his
as his um as his
um
career advances but but the point
here is it's expressionism so it is
that he wants to pour out what's
invisible
to the scientific community and to
modernity
and you can can't be put in three
dimensions
and which is probably why he goes
fractal and probably why he goes like
okay there's just no way to express i
could draw an image but it will just
translate into something else i'm just
gonna express it purely
and yeah and that's on the other side
then
of so you see these post modernities
multi-perspectivalism revolt against
modernity
you have um uh authenticity
this the same as in early early
20th century aesthetics like in in the
study of aesthetic with walter benjamin
you have
that that he he brings up these exact
themes
now eventually in the at the pinnacle of
post-modernism you get to
you find that when this this post
modernism of course also is a wave or a
move so you find aha we go from
modernity is moving wow wow wow we can
shift the directions and perspectives of
it hello picasso and then
we then we go to wait a minute uh we're
we're not really getting to the to the
core of it we also need
to really really really fully and truly
express
ourselves and then you kind of go on a
full 7 because nobody's really home
and what you end up is like wait a
minute there's no difference between art
and anything else this is just one out
of many games
and here we are trying to shape this
thing
and if there is no clear progress and
there are no clear dimensions
and uh and we need to be critical at
least we can
just admit that art
fine art the fine arts are not different
from from
the rest of culture including popular
arts
and we can admit that the world is flat
that there wasn't so much depth in there
after all
and that once you turn these things
around many times enough
you notice a certain kind of flatness of
predictability to it
that the artists themselves will be
playing roles will be putting on a show
and so on and
voila we have warhol
and then we end with a postmodern
cynicism
now today you go to contemporary arts
museum and unfortunately
i mean they're they're nice and fun in a
way
but new stuff usually is a little bit
boring
because we kind of been stuck in a rut
here because then the arts have been
defined as
okay so this is what's ours what the
arts are
we're gonna do roughly these things and
then people do roughly these things
and it was fun and cool when it was
invented
but nowadays it's alienating and a
little bit boring
and then it also alienates the middle
class or
uh like i'm just not not art interested
people and
there's a kind of culture war because
then then
the the idea would be of course that
well if you can't appreciate this you're
not educated enough or
where you don't have enough style or
class or etcetera and people of course
gonna fight that narrative and they're
gonna say you're a phony
uh so so right now we're in this kind of
embittered
uh battle and we've been stuck here for
basically since
since world's time um
and and really it is phony a lot of it
just just frankly and it is stuck in a
rut and people are right
to to to revolt against it
[Music]
um so we're getting there towards
a meta modern metameme so why did i pick
a solar punk image well
there are a couple of ideas linked to
this well first of all i think solar
pump could be
a good outlet for for uh
for uh meta modern projects out there in
the world
i think uh today unfortunately
non-democratic countries or societies i
should say like singapore
uh kind of have the upper hand when it
comes to creating
very engaging and like
full spectrum experience uh aesthetic
urban livable spaces right and
and uh democratic societies uh
well we're the ones looking drab kind of
like
uh kind of like in the um
in the 1900s with east berlin and west
berlin the east berlins would like
to save up like wow this is a cornflakes
package i'm going to save it here and
yeah just because it kind of looked
shiny and they wanted this glow and
yeah and they wanted an abba
lp or whatever and and right now
actually
the the non-democratic societies tend to
have that
and people will go to singapore and
they'll come home and and
say stuff like they would have said on
like 100
or maybe 70 years ago when they went to
the states right the
states oh which was so impressive was so
shiny
but but no more right that people say
well the streets were shoddy blah blah
blah blah
poverty um and
whereas whereas people go to singapore
and they say it's an ideal society and
well you know you can't replace the
government
so so um so uh
where am i going with this well i think
we need aesthetic movements
like these that could be take up the
metamodern space so of course i mean
admittedly it's also a little bit corny
but it can it
leaves some some
it doesn't have all the it doesn't
include
quite enough of the post-modern irony
and distance
it's a little bit too utopian sure you
can see
they did include that rust has has
has run on some of the some of the
um signs here and so on but the point
here is that
we're going into a position where
po meta modernism is defined of course
as the diff has the
extrapolation or extrapolation or
um the oscillation between modern and
postmodern so you include
the modern progress and so on
and you include also the postmodern
distance and self-critique and in a way
it actually puts us back
a lot in this space here where we were
with
futurism it's a very dangerous place to
be we start imagining futures we start
seeing
digital society can can melt things away
really fast we can destroy whole worlds
and we can create whole worlds and we
can
we can uh create a transcendent
shared experience of creating new worlds
that we want to live in
and though that that should hopefully be
a deeply democratic
or more democratic um
and fair and open process than current
societies in the west not less
democratic
oh and and now we're kind of in this
futurist space where
there's again a totalitarian
spectre kind of urging our song whoa
we could do all this we what if one one
ring rules then all how beautiful could
it be it could be huge we could make
cathedrals of what like like you never
dreamt of
in virtual worlds and and uh if we just
lend a little bit extra control to a few
great artists who will change the world
well
and this was exactly what the nazis also
how they described themselves they said
well
the people is our marble and we're the
artists this is an exact
quote from um give us
um so uh guess the meta meme
i think like solar punk scene looks like
an ally but
there's a family of these things there's
xeno feminism like hmm
well i mean like we start looking
at not we start like unmarrying
this this this
[Music]
da vinci image and we start like wait a
minute i kind of
see i'm like a cow but the cow has other
properties of its
xeno morph body and i'm just a xenomorph
of this and we can play around with that
and they're well that's kind of more of
the delhi direction the doll
like salvador the lead direction of in
the meta modern space but
but we could go in a bunch of different
directions here when we can play
with we're going to deeply reshape
society at this point
um i'm going to go on
so here i i'm going to
land in something i think is met a
modern art and and help
help point out some differences between
post-modern metamodern
but i first want to talk about i've been
talking about the
meta means so historical huge
structural generated functions in
cultures
but human beings are also carriers of
these and we are body categories of
these and we our
own and body carrier like our own
embodied like
cultural development or whatever is i
called valium a lot of other people
called valemi
effective value so let's at the same
time
in this very same culture you'll have
the value memes diverging and creating
different forms of art
or different aesthetic expressions i
should like to say
um and looking at these two
guess the value meme okay i'm not sure
how well you're getting this one
um how well you're getting this image
i can maybe no i can't make it bigger uh
previous guess the volume
so um like
if you look at this it's fairly glossy
and it's kind of obvious and in in that
it's
tries to be like whoa
like if this is going to be the next
level with big
and it's kind of like a kid did it in
many ways like and
uh it would kind of like i don't know
speak to a
10 year old fantasy book or a 12 year
old or whatever
um and and it's
like it it's a little bit too obvious it
tries a little bit too much
it doesn't it doesn't have self irony
not that i'm aware of
maybe all of this is an ironic stunt i'm
not sure what we're looking at here is
the
is the flat earth society and this is
their symbol and this is how they
present at a conference and you can also
see with the coloring and so on
so what i'm getting at here is that the
flat earth society even
using all the modern stuff
in our day and age um
i can bring this here so yeah using all
this
stuff in the modern age um they still
express
a fairly low value
so and this is interesting right you
swing
like that's how you can see
which things are going to work
with a with a more complex global
culture and which things
aren't right so on a on a very visceral
level
and i'm not exactly sure what the method
is here
but to me it's fairly obvious like well
this
looks simple
hysterical corny whatever and it looks
low value meme um
so and that's that just means
that it won't include
a lot of the for instance postmodern
stuff a lot of the modern stuff
it will express another kind of culture
right
which is fine we want a broad expression
but
the point i'm making here is that beauty
then is uh is
allied to different expressions of um
of uh power relations and different
that they're they're battling each other
out different aesthetics right so some
people are gonna want
reality and society to have certain
expressions
now uh this one to the left or
to the right you can say the same thing
right um
alpha baptist church like i i can't even
say
why you know but somehow it's i mean
it's just
terribly uncool um and
why is that i'm not sure but let's look
at it well
well there there's something about how
it tries to be
really modern and and
and and yet isn't um
and somehow also that the message is not
into it it doesn't leave a lot to for
the
interpreter of the message the only one
road leads to having jesus christ is the
way
it also says right so it kind of puts it
in your face
right and it doesn't leave a lot of
space for interpretation
it doesn't have this neither the
authenticity neither the
the multi-dimensionality neither that
we're shaping this
thing as it goes faster and faster of
futurism and nor
the uh nor the irony of course of uh
warhol so those those post-modern
elements are entirely
gone so now it gets touchy
the next one what it gets the value
name of this
so we sit down with it for a moment so
okay this is
contemporary art it's from our days
um and it is
um it's about spiritual and psychedelic
experience right
and we can we can see that i mean
there's a genuine profundity to this
artist right
because well he might also have might
also have faked it by
looking at something else but but
there's a genuine spiritual profanity
if we take it at face value that that
he's expressing he's making this up
himself right
uh and what what does he see well he
notices that
the world is more colorful and
and sharply colorful than our eyes
normally see
he notices there there is an intricate
pattern that connects
all things behind he notice there there
are vast spaces and vast openings
beyond you and inside you and that there
is no clear boundary between the inner
and the outer
all of these are expressed that there is
an ideal self a kind of
shines in this go golden light of this
dawn that you see
in this and this is of course
well alex don't remember his name but
it's like the the number one integralist
uh alex something his uh
his uh the number one integralist artist
and this is
this art piece of art is also exemplary
of the other major movement
of what people have said should
should and can and will come after post
modernism
um that there's a next developmental
stage after post-modern and they called
integral or
or and i've been very much part of this
as well and and feel
still feel closely bound to this
movement but
looking at the aesthetics i mean we
should be suspicious here
why well it doesn't include
self-iron and it doesn't leave a lot
for a difference of perspectives and it
doesn't leave
a lot for um
[Music]
well it's there's nothing it really put
i mean it's not very far away from this
if we think about it
oh the only one road leads to heaven
jesus christ is the way
is not so far away from that and it just
i mean this literally points at some
kind of a mega point over there
uh this is how shiny things are gonna be
if you
have a spiritual experience if you're
integral if you buy into our kind of
spirituality
um and hey what
and just like more more fundamentally we
put this up like let's say i have this
strong spiritual experience
and i look at alex yeah
this guy's a painting and i put it up on
the wall
and then i bring in my friend who
doesn't have the same experience and
doesn't have the same
um the same um
ideas about integralism and so on
what will he think of me or she
they will think that i'm a little bit
hysterical
that i'm deluding myself and
um that i believe in woo-woo stuff
and chances are they would be right
so i mean metamodernism the reason
that we picked up metamodernis as a term
instead of integralism well there were a
few others as well but the main one
is a design intervention it's like
this is the generator function they try
to place the the aesthetic generator
function they try to place
to create this super inclusive
multi-perspectival movement that will
integrate all of the form of metamoves
now that doesn't make a lot of sense
because the aesthetics are too corny
and they're going to exclude most of the
people and they're going to lead to
magical thinking
and they're going to be too hysterical
and they're going to lead to the
creation of cults which they have
uh laura you wanted to break in oh yeah
i just wanted to say
that we are at the hour mark just you
know yeah okay wonderful oh
i always talk longer than i imagined
this looked so small in my brain when i
yeah okay sorry uh
okay go on and on uh guess the value
mean
i i i wasn't nervous when i started i
didn't have enough to say
hey uh guess the value mean here then
so this is what you get if you google
meta modern
art um and then
artists much more sophisticated than
myself in the art world and so on
or artists or at least art scholars they
they they bring up
examples such as these and they discuss
them in long
frankly often pretty boring uh papers
but uh they have something
uh going on like which i do think
they're on to
there is something going on here like
what do we get in this first one
um you get um
that you have um um
you have realism
yes it looks fairly realistic this could
be the real world
but at the same time there's a slight
hint of fantasy in there right
and you get indigenous
aspects but in a modern setting which is
solar pump but not
excessive solar punk not
where so will punch on steroid solar
punk but just a little bit
and and it leaves a lot unknown a lot
unsaid what is this place who lives
there
why did they construct it um and
it looks like a church kind of so it's
probably a spiritual place but we
we don't know exactly uh so the the
point here is that
you have well some kind of critical
reappraisal reappraisal of
former effective or
former meta memes um
but it's not in your face and you have
some kind of spirituality some kind of
hope of some kind of different future
but it's pretty subtle and that's kind
of the space we want to be in
for meta-modern art same here
like you see this boy he's in a mundane
setting
but there's still something magical
about the picture and where is the map
does the magic come from
it comes from just the natural world
just the reality he looks at himself
in this melting ice pot
pond and and you kind of get a magical
sense but you can't exactly say where
the magic is coming from
but it's terribly mundane at the same
time
it's fairly magical like
seriously which is the most spiritual
this one
or that one well maybe this one is more
spiritual in terms of
in terms of like it describes a more
far-out experience it does
but i kind i mean the kind of
spirituality
that i feel more often connected to
is better expressed than this one so
this is more
met in modern art and i think that the
modern art scholars many of whom or most
of whom wouldn't like
myself who who is the modern political
philosopher
and has an explicit program with what i
do and so on
um very very very much on to something
here
and this kind of aesthetic is how
i think movements for the future a much
more careful
movement for the future should be should
be looking um it's
and we also kind of get rid of the
hysterical movement there in the
futurism
ah okay this was actually it so i want
to say one more thing
so um mad and modern
art uh
it get we gets a little bit confusing
then when
we well actually i'll say two things
first of all we reintroduce magic and
hope vis-a-vis
the post-modern art so that's that's the
main that's the main difference there
we also reintroduced more
of craftsmanship so those those two
last paintings we looked at
[Music]
if you show up because of yourself you
have to explain why somebody
why this wasn't made by your
untalented neighbor like we're just any
random person off the street
you have to explain it now this you
don't actually have to explain that
an artist has made it right and that's
different so reintroduce that
part which is from i mean of course
takes us back
uh all the way to
uh these paintings like it's clear that
there's this was an
artist who made this that i was a crafts
man who made this so uh so we put craft
back and put hope back we put magic in
but
but we put in like we didn't put in 99
magic we put in 4 magic
so most people can just walk past it and
never be offended
but it still has sublimity now
the last thing i wanted to say here
is what we don't want is because
metamodernism is used in different terms
in different ways
different different uh different
uh ways of grasping it
or like delineating it it also has it
has both political
implications and and aesthetic and
philosophical and
and what not uh spiritual will get to
and
but think about socialist art
socialist art didn't fly
they thought socialism was a higher
stage of society that comes after
capitalist society
and then they start they say okay so i'm
a
socialist artist yeah yeah i'm socialist
and the the state would say yeah yeah we
want
social start and they allied up with
some futurist artists and so on and they
designed
this this style which was cool for a
while and then
basically in the end socialist art that
became
whatever stalin likes
and something was good and a lot of it
wasn't
but the point is that
you can't do that so we're not looking
for like
a a book of like this is
meta modernist art approved by the state
or whatever
the modernist community we have
that's not where we're going so be
careful when we approach this
it's it's just a way and then
for this reason of course uh the the
metamodern art scholars are
rightly careful about being prescriptive
because it just doesn't quite belong in
this
this category now for for last one
before we do a round of questions and so
on i'm sorry i've
uh again
broken every reasonable time limit sorry
about this
also i'm going to try and move this
blooms
i want to show this let's see if i can
one moment guys
how common brief on it
[Music]
well that's as far as we got okay let's
go for one moment
we will never mind
uh you guys still hear me yep uh
so uh so um what do i want to say about
this
well so what we have here is john ed
marks
he is harvard or something and he
um he makes these sculptures in
mathematician
so what i would say this is where we
want that modern art
to be going it doesn't look like art
anymore it already escaped
the art uh gallery
and in the art galleries that the most
progressive artists they like to go in
and look in the labs why because the
true
truth seeking of scientists reveals
crazy
structures and just weirdest weirdest
visual effects and
like mind-boggling effects that you can
think of
and they want to play with that and
what happens then in the meta modern
this metamodern move
of art is that truth and truth seeking
is reintroduced
and like uh but at an even more literal
level
than in the modern project when and it's
placed at the center and heart
of the meta modern arts project
which then expresses higher and more
transcendental beauty
as an expression of truth
so mathematical truths in these
movements
become these sculptures they become
alive they are mesmerizing
they are eye-opening and so on um
but we didn't place we didn't fall for
the temptation to place beauty first
we saw that if we follow truth
and we try to speak truth at all times
find out what's true even if it hurts
then play with it
then we will create that greater beauty
if we
which is like i mean at this tempting
moment here
uh what you find in populism and
and at the end other end of that spec
at the end of that road fascism is
you you define truth or you define
beauty and then you try to press it upon
the world your beauty
and you forget about the
multi-perspectivalism you forget about
the authenticity you forget about the
necessary from that flatness of it all
and and and that's that's a real
that's a real danger so so i want to say
that um this
this aesthetic new movement that
is subtly taking form and
i'm sure you guys can find many more and
better examples and i have
um it can and should be a
movement where um beauty follows from
truth
and is somehow yet its transcendental
quality um yeah i'll stop there
and yeah sorry for taking so long
again
can i stop sharing stop sharing
i'll bear to you
great yeah thanks for thanks for your
presentation
so um we have lots of questions in the
chat
so let's start with rob hart
because he got some plus ones rob would
you like to
unmute yourself and ask how consciously
does the artist
express the generator function of the
culture
how much of the expression is an overt
effort to capture and express the
normativity of the culture and how much
of it is accidental or unconscious on
the artist's part
and would that answer change depending
on the culture's value meme
so in any way you can say
that each each step is within a
you know you kind of climb out of the
former you try to
try to answer to that so
uh animist uh tries to climb out of a
direct
uh non-representational part of being a
non-representational part of nature we
say like
we're actually not just nature we we're
also seeing spirits and stuff we're also
depicting nature
and um and then you go from there
to um to like actually
we're not part of nature at all we we're
we have our own universe and
our own gods and and there's a god for
this and god for that and then
like no actually actually there's
we can climb out of that and there's
just one universal truth
on it goes uh and the the most
the most self-conscious it of course
becomes at
post-modernism or where it's you know
entirely
about being a self-conscious artist
which comments upon your society
and then trying to express something
else now that being said
there's no correlation between having
this particular
idea about meta memes and doing
what you do like expressing
something through some medium by
destroying something else
like there's there's no correlation at
all so 99.9
plus something percent of all artists
are going to do it
automatically in this in the sense that
they don't
sit down with me hear this model
and then express it obviously so yeah
but so there's a both kind of both
answer it's all super automatic
unless you consider that everybody is of
course reacting to
the former kind of or expressing
against the background of the former
great um i one thing i forgot to note um
please try and keep your follow-up
questions
or statements to one or two with that
rob did you have anything to follow up
with
well i you know i agree and appreciate
what you say about
they don't study the models before they
produce the art
and then i'm fascinated by the idea that
they're trying to climb out of
the maybe the current movement that
they're in
and i wonder is the challenge of being
stuck in the rut with post-modernity
that there's nothing left to climb
out of
um so i think
i mean i don't think
the egyptians fell stuck in a rut we
only feel stuck in iraq because we
expect
certain things remarked we say it's
going to be new it's going to be
shocking it's going to be mind-boggling
and so on right
and it's going to comment upon reality
it will comment upon
society and it's and therefore the
hundredth time
in a row somebody says well i made this
it comments upon
how we view migration and it's well
and it kind of kind of always are those
same things and they're critical against
that they don't really
present any solution
it's unclear entirely what you should
actually do with it
it problematizes rather than creates and
so on
um and then people are rightly
left with you know sense of resistance
against this
and oftentimes this you know a load of
tax money
goes into these projects so we're stuck
because we kind of have that expectation
and then
i mean to get from one
thousand meme or or a special one uh
one metamean to the next there's a huge
gravity i mean
all of the reference this person has
ever seen and all of their upbringing
bring them
just post-modern ideas and first there
are low-hanging fruits people like them
but there's a whole renaissance going on
everybody's having lots of fun
uh everybody's inventing cool new stuff
uh then after a while there are no more
low-hanging fruits
you have to get to the next level or
stage
of of cultural development but to do
that you have to go against
all that you already know and then then
you tend to be stuck for a while
um yeah
great um so lisa hogan had a question
that i am going to read for her uh as we
move towards new technology and further
mechanization of our lives bodies minds
etc
how do you think this evolution will
impact the generator function
so it's a very good question the the
fundamental
issue then is that art
from being undifferentiated from other
topics
to becoming in modernity like religion
like
a bunch of other things a specific
category two being challenged as such
under post-modernity uh and and kind of
leaking out
other other things but just challenge
just at the edges the
modern promise is to break it out
of that um of its confines
into leaking out like like
yeah that's why solar pump is so good
because
it's like it's a fantasy image
but yet it's what's literally happening
in in some cities
and what most people would probably want
a lot of our
urban landscapes to look like and it's
doable and it has something to do with
uh both urban design and um and
architecture and uh
and sustainable living and climate
change and the rest of it
and resilience uh so
and of course energy systems
uh so it is in the space of
not being real and being real at the
same time like being
so virtual that becomes hyper real so
what meta-modern art will be will
probably
not be that's an interesting quite
little modern
uh like um exhibition
at the of the metropolitan it's
not that it breaks out of that prison
and then transforms life itself becomes
which
will then make our our lives much more
like a work of art
which is then a deeper liberation for
emancipation of
ourselves and our relationships um
so that's a and that we the
the generator function will be richer
than which means that
the sheer number of combinations of
things that can be invented
become larger which means a higher
expressiveness or or uniqueness shows up
among many different people now
of course then you also destroy more
things
when you create you also wreck
which means that the risk of this whole
thing falling apart and becoming
either fascism or mad max society is
very big
all right so alexandra had another
question um
that people were uploading alexander
would you like to ask
yeah sure um i was wondering whether
metamod and
at could be described as one that
supports
relationship between and elicits
resonance
in a series of value means eg fractal
patterns
yes hi alexander by the way
uh so i agree
but i say i agree
but it's not necessarily
so so meta modern art
is first of all we break through from
what we normally see
as art we um we intuit
something profound without putting it
in your face too much we
introduce craftsmanship through
craftsmanship
and we try to be more perspectival and
integrative
of many different meta means or
perspectives but
it's kind of in a cloud or like a venn
diagram of these things
so if you lack it's like wait a minute
this this artwork doesn't integrate uh
east or west
or listen to our uh like i see no post
particular post-posting elements in this
one
then this can't be meta-modern well we
don't want a checklist
like that right and the interval lists
uh
they they used to think a little bit
like that uh that
well you have these different color
codes and you have to include everyone
checklist check check check okay then
this is individual
no i think you missed that one that's
that's not how it works rather
because it on a subtle level
becomes inclusive enough to be both
transcendent and and critical
and all of those things but at the same
time you can just walk past it
if it's not your thing it won't register
it won't i necessarily um
you also i mean they hate
i'm not even sure let yeah
that's that's a difficult question you
could also say like with wallace
uh like that they are the guy who wrote
infinite jest
that um metamodern literature is gonna
make some people very very
happy and some people are very very sad
and angry and
and you can imagine it that way as well
right that
you consciously or deliberately draw
upon dialectical relationships or
intuitively dummies doesn't even have to
be consciously
and and and you um
and you piss some people off a lot right
so
so anyway yeah you play with the
sensitivity
towards the many that that's as far as i
go you play with the sensitivity towards
the many
many memes
did you have any follow-up alexandria
just a brief resonance like i
i wonder whether meta modern art could
death will never really be something
fixed in time like it always has to be
in in movement somehow
because otherwise you're sort of
really risking to miss the point of
wanting to
break people out of their conflict but
yeah
just just that
yeah uh maybe maybe
um um
[Music]
yeah maybe i i mean at the same time
it's like um
it will probably make sense to to to
uh in a hundred years look at a bunch of
things that happen in our culture today
and
put in an art book next to the next to
the other ones then
and probably can be static in that sense
but at the same time if you look at
modernity
like renaissance paintings today and
500 years ago obviously the thing has
moved and this thing is going to move a
lot more you look at post-modernity
there's a huge difference between a
futurist painting
and the wall and nevertheless they're in
the same family
but it's been on the move and then kind
of stopped at a new world
and then people are complaining that
being complained about it got boring
right
so daniel do you have time for one or
two more questions yes i do actually
i um i realized i didn't actually have
to eating
right after this great okay
so um travis had a question would you
like to
uh meet and ask yeah thanks
uh when i was looking at them meta
modernist examples i picked up on some
transcendentalist vibes like
emersonian or thoreauian
if that's even the way that you would
say that is that
uh explicit is this kind of uh
are they picking up the thread of the
naturalism of transcendentalist thinking
and maybe trying to reconcile that with
the pervasiveness of
the man-made systems that kind of
dominate the
post-modern world and so
okay travis i'll just have to pass
on that question because um hey i mean
like i said i'm really not an expert on
the paintings themselves
and but i'm sure there is an answer to
that
and my my gut feeling is yes yes
there is definitely some emersonian
tendencies in there and i also think
generally speaking this american kind of
spirituality
um and mysticism
has a lot of proto and modern elements
right because i mean there's a
connection to pragmatism
to things on the move to taking up
multiple perspectives
to be you know in depth
driven and spirituality driven uh and
and go after profound
expressions of existence without uh
without teaching science and and so so
there are
yeah there's also a sense of
reconnecting to earlier
earlier meta memes and with with uh
reconnecting to nature and so on um
so yes i i think it's
unmistakably there but if that's just if
you ask
me you're just saying yeah i we agree
but uh asking some of the experts or the
artists themselves they might actually
have giving you
another answer thanks
all right um paul had a question um that
seems to reference
uh what you were talking about a little
earlier paul would you like to
um hey daniel i'd be curious as to
um the relationship basically between
the good true beautiful and in that
sense
you said that truth comes first so
why beauty comes second kind of makes
sense um but why not the good
or what is the place for the good in
this
actually yeah so so i figured it makes
sense
um to actually discuss about
either truth uh either either good or
justice as
as a category i mean look at that
plato's big four
we do have that um
so
the the good and the the true and the
beautiful
you can expand it into a four like
wilbur
has four quadrants for instance and then
he never really names the fourth
quadrant
and in these terms but uh i mean you
could you could also say
uh the first person reality
is has to do with beauty because
no but because it's this transcendent
quality
nobody can take from you if you think
it's something that's beautiful or
or not a second person a
second person is has to do with goodness
and
justice because once you and i are there
then then we can treat each other
morally or not morally we can agree upon
that there's a true
value to that i guess in a sense and
then there is objective truth value that
once you and i are there we can look at
a third thing
at an object or a third person and say
this is a lion
and you're saying no it's a pigeon and
then we don't agree and then eventually
we bring another person to the table
three of us look and
yeah and two people agree that it's a
pigeon not alive for instance
and so that's third person reality and
then you could expand it to fourth
person reality which is the perspective
or on the method we use to check if it's
a pigeon or
so so we checked all all
incumbents for pigeon bias and turns out
you you had terrible pigeon bites
and and then we can change the
perspective
so now we can imagine
that the arts uh or the expression of
human agency upon other objects which
are
creative and destructive and have
some aesthetic qualities to them that
they can look to these different forms
of um
they can look at these different forms
of of relatedness um to reality itself
now given uh
the entrance of post-modern art you
enter into perspectivalism you enter
into fourth person round
because it's not just a modern
sense of reality out there not just
three dimensions
[Music]
picasso can squeeze a bunch of
dimensions and do the same thing right
so uh looking at to get back to your
question
uh more precisely what
what the good is is
um entirely actually
it it can you can only know the good
by knowing and what
how you and i will treat each other once
we have a relationship up
now there's a the the good will be
shaped by what you and i agree is
beautiful
so uh oftentimes different
different ethics out there babbling in
the world for
i don't know capitalist ethics against
communist ethics and so on
will take on uh um
an aesthetic side to them and
for some people it just feels nice to
think about animal rights it sounds cool
for some people it just sounds boring
and and
a bit pantsy and those are aesthetic
qualities
so uh the the
good we generally get by working
through the intersection of the true and
the perspective
and that we kind of have to travel
up up those of that
up that pyramid of abstraction or
whatever
into the perspective then we go all the
way back down
so so on the way down to the to the
beauty and where we recreate with ut
once we have found new profound truths
together
uh in a larger multiplicity of
perspectives
then we also on the way down figure out
the ethics
and the the point the only point is that
a lot of people out there will find
well i think this looks cool so then it
is the good
which is fine but it shouldn't be
ultimately
how how the it should the good should
ultimately be reduced
uh because the good will be
what is beautiful to you and me and then
a compromise between those
and if we compromise too far we can make
a reality entirely black
so we can't let the good or justice eat
up all the beauty in the world
because we'll end up being in concrete
buildings
with every penny we try to use on
culture
somebody will say wait a minute isn't
this better to use on medicine
or whatever and
and then we will live in a world devoid
of beauty
so somehow
yeah yeah some somehow we have to go all
the way up and all the way down
through these and and reconnect
back to beauty which is where life
really happens it doesn't happen some
perspective doesn't happen in truth
seeking
it doesn't happen even in ethics it just
happens
when there is an enjoyment um etc
which is always a participatory
enjoyment of of
meeting the world which is an aesthetic
experience and thus what art is
ultimately about
whether or not we want to use the modern
category of art or not
all right so there's one more question i
thought might be nice to end us off with
uh hopefully it's not opening anything
too uh
extensive here but um dan feldman you
had a question about
hope
um yeah i'm trying to recall i don't
see it in front of me at the moment i i
guess my question with regard you said
the new ecstatic
uh daniel was based upon
uh subtlety craftsmanship
and i guess multi-perspectivalism as
well as hope
and i am questioning
the value of hope um that perhaps that
um brings in um
it enters in that nihilism that we don't
sit in the trouble long enough
you know it's like give me that hope
medicine quickly so i don't
sit in the ruins and my own crap long
enough that i can get through it
it's kind of this deny it it feeds into
this denialism
that i it's gaslighting this narcissism
that i think we're
embedded in so i'm i'm very allergic to
the concept that the art should have
anything to do
with any um blatant or explicit or
conscious hope
and i'm wondering what your uh sense of
that is
no so so i i would have to disagree on a
fundamental uh
behavioral level so if you don't have
hope like let's say
um let's say you're gonna have breakfast
if you don't have any hope
of it nourishing you and you feeling
full
afterwards um
[Music]
or it tasting well you know if
if the hope level is literally brought
to zero
you won't be able to get yourself to eat
breakfast it's i'm just just
and doesn't have to end with character
or or
or something it's just like if my hope
level for
you know giving this talk with and and
so on was that like
yeah i'm not going to get through with
anything i'm going to have anything to
say
and etc right so i'm just just on that
visceral basic level
we do need hope because we cannot act
without in the world without we can
if we with hope just mean expectation
of outcome which is
desirable right uh a reasonable
expectation of outcome
uh so um um so so
i mean today why do you think we do have
a lack of hope
and i see what you mean i see like yeah
we also have a
like a bunch of denial mechanisms and
yeah i'm not
like i'm not talking empirical i'm not
saying
uh we're gonna make it like we don't
know if we're gonna make
i it i'm empirically not very hopeful
right i'm talking about spiritual
meaning
that we have uh fuel enough
like to lead not miserable lives and
then still
find awesome things to be doing together
and be playful about it
and kind of just you know act
on something and i think silver punk is
a good example there
like i said okay i see what you mean
because i also
i also think there's a little bit of
hysteria and
people have a level other critiques to
it you know it's too gentrified to white
whatever
um too glossy maybe but but
uh but what i mean is uh like yeah we
kill all hope with
paddy warhol and then we make sure it
says that
but once we've killed all hope what do
we do well
it's the same thing with god we will get
to this
if you join a later talk on the fourth
talk in this series
uh like once you've killed god like
what's left to do well you resurrect him
or her with it or i am
um and it always comes back on the third
day
and it's kind of like that after
deconstruction right and we're talking
ruthless deconstruction we're gonna pick
this world apart
ruthlessly and pick ourselves apart
it's gonna be painful it's gonna be
awful and it already is awful
but what do you do afterwards
when everything is disenchanted like
like
once we've really done our homework well
then i think we
deserve some hope and then i think we
should
come up with a most often art project we
can think of
which means just pure uh creation of
cool and and find the highest possible
truth that can follow and then try to
work together to make it happen
um and you know basically coming out of
the box like
the thing on the screen that is today of
fantasy will be real
here in the world that's hope or like
well we get
close to uh fiction but the fiction gets
the closer we get to it the more it
becomes real
and then it's no longer fiction and then
reality
over uh overturns fiction
and and and it becomes more fantastic
because
route always surprises us it's always
more horrible than we imagined
and then it's always more fantastic than
we imagined right
um yeah i mean i i guess
it's not a rational argument to get to
give back i mean the first part may be
about behavior
thing but it's it's just uh i guess
people have different
religious ground settings here and i
think
um yeah it's nothing to argue about
really it's just
it's just the thing that yeah we're
gonna have different
basic feelings about this right
well awesome so that will have to be it
for this session
thank you daniel for uh taking us on
this journey through
art history and the modern movement and
art
um is there anything you'd like to wrap
us up with
no just a big thank you to uh
questioners
i see some some friends in the the
little boxes thanks to you laura you've
been great thanks
peter for making this happen um
yeah hoping to deepen and continue this
throughout the month awesome so i'm
going to tag peter in
thank you all beautiful
thank you laura thank you daniel thank
you everyone for the excellent questions
uh just to talk about a couple events
happening today
um we have peter jones uh
he's a professor from ocad university
he's influential in the kind of sense
making design space
he's having a talk called living with
the global problematique
and this is sort of discussing at the
club of rome when they're 20 and the 49
continuous critical problems that they
discussed
like basically the meta crisis and how
to kind of live
in this age that we're in and then
that's at six p.m eastern time and then
right after that we got another sense
making residents daniel schmuckerberger
coming in
uh that's the digital porch and that's
no agenda
no subject we're just gonna come in
daniel's gonna sit on the digital
portion we're going to ask some
questions
so that should be fun and that's at 7 30
pm eastern time
and in the same link uh tyson wagner is
going to have rap
unbattles uh it's a new session where
instead of like tearing each other down
through rap battles
we're building each other up uh through
rap on battles
so you can rcp on that link below and
let me just add a few uh
links to the website the patreon and the
sub stack
that being said again everyone thank you
for coming to the store today
thank you everyone please thank you